<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>golang on Dev&#39;s Log</title>
    <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/tags/golang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in golang on Dev&#39;s Log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Tran Duc Ngoc</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://idev-blog.web.app/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Pipelines and cancellation</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/concurrency-pattern-pipeline-and-cancellation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/concurrency-pattern-pipeline-and-cancellation/</guid>
      <description>Go&amp;rsquo;s concurrency primitives make it easy to construct streaming data pipelines that make efficient use of I/O and multiple CPUs. This article introduces what is pipeline, how to to construct a pipeline and introduces techniques for dealing with failures cleanly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Channel Use Case in Golang</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-usecase/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-usecase/</guid>
      <description>This article will show many channel use cases
Asynchronous and concurrency programing with Go channels is easy and enjoyable. The channel synchronization technique has wider range of uses and have more variables than the synchronization solutions used in some other languages, such as the actor model and the async/await pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Channel in Golang</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-in-golang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-in-golang/</guid>
      <description>Channel is an important built-in feature in Go. It is one of the features makes Go unique. Channel makes concurrent programming convenient, fun and lowers the difficulties of concurrent programming. Channel mainly acts as a concurrency synchronization technique. To understand channels better, the internal structure of channels and some implementation details by the standard Go compiler/runtime are also simply described.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generator and Future Pattern</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/concurrency-pattern-generator-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/concurrency-pattern-generator-future/</guid>
      <description>Generator Pattern allows the consumer of the data produced by the generator to run in parallel when the generator function is busy computing the next value.
A Future indicates any data that is needed in future but its computation can be started in parallel so that it can be fetched from the background when needed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
