<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ngoctd on Dev&#39;s Log</title>
    <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/authors/ngoctd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ngoctd on Dev&#39;s Log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Tran Duc Ngoc</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 14:09:50 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://idev-blog.web.app/authors/ngoctd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Awesome resources collector</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/awesome-resource-collector/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 14:09:50 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/awesome-resource-collector/</guid>
      <description>Data Race Patterns in Go A data race is a concurrency bug that occurs when two or more goroutines access the same datum, at least one of them is write, and there is no ordering between them. Data races are insidious bug and must be avoided at all costs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Một vài cách sử dụng channel trong golang</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/golang-channel-usecase/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/golang-channel-usecase/</guid>
      <description>Lập trình bất đồng bộ (asynchronous) và đồng thời (concurrency) trở lên dễ dàng với channel trong Golang. Synchronization với channel có phạm vi sử dụng lớn và nhiều biến thể hơn so với các mô hình khác như actoc model hay async/await pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automatic connect to VPN</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/linux-auto-connect-openvpn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/linux-auto-connect-openvpn/</guid>
      <description>The OpenVPN is an open source Virtual Private Network (VPN) project. It creates secure connections over the Internet using a custom security protocol that utilizes SSL/TLS.
In this article, i will introduce naive solution for automatic connect to VPN using openvpn and systemd management.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Channel in Golang</title>
      <link>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-in-golang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://idev-blog.web.app/posts/programming-language-channel-in-golang/</guid>
      <description>Channel is an important built-in feature in Go. It is one of the features makes Go unique. Channel makes concurrent programming convenient, fun and lowers the difficulties of concurrent programming. Channel mainly acts as a concurrency synchronization technique. To understand channels better, the internal structure of channels and some implementation details by the standard Go compiler/runtime are also simply described.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
